A Finding Aid to the Wilbur H. Burnham Studios Records, circa 1904-1991, in the Archives of American Art AAA.wilbhbur
Archives of American Art
Wilbur H. Burnham Studios records
circa 1904-1991
AAA.wilbhbur
Archives of American Art
35.2 Linear feet
The records of nationally renowned Boston, Massachussetts, stained glass design company, Wilbur H. Burnham Studios, measure 35.2 linear feet and date from circa 1904-1991. The majority of the collection consists of project files for the studio's stained glass window contracts throughout the United States from the 1920s-1980s. In addition to project files, records include biographical material for the owners, correspondence relating to personal and studio business, general business and financial records, writings such as published articles by Wilbur H. Burnham, scrapbooks and other printed material documenting the history of the company, artwork including extensive watercolor design studies for stained glass, and photographic material.
Wilbur H. Burnham Studios
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Wilbur H. Burnham Studios records were donated in 7 accesions by Wilbur H. Burnham, Jr., from 1977-1981 and by Wilbur C. Burnham, grandson of the founder, in 1990-1991. Scott McDaniel, co-owner of the firm, contributed to the 1990 donation.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Historical Note
Boston, Massachussets stained glass design firm, Wilbur H. Burnham Studios, was founded by master stained glass craftsman Wilbur H. Burnham, in 1922. Together with Charles J. Connick and Joseph G. Reynolds, Burnham studios became recognized as one of the most prominent stained glass design companies in the United States. Burnham took early commissions from influential American architect Ralph Adams Cram, and believed strongly in the medieval stained glass tradition. In the late 1930s his son, Wilbur H. Burnham, Jr., who had received an informal education on tours of Europe with his family, and a BFA from Yale University, joined the firm.
Some of the studio's most notable commissions included seventeen windows for the Washington National Cathedral in Washington, D. C., all the windows and murals for Saint Mary's Cathedral, Peoria, Illinois, ten windows for the Cathedral of Saint John the Divine in New York City, and five for the Riverside Church, also in New York City.
Both Burnham and Burnham, Jr., served as presidents of the Stained Glass Association of American from 1938-1941 and 1956-1957 respectively. Burnham, Jr., took over the studio in 1968 when his father retired, and sold the studios in 1982.
Scope and Content Note
The records of nationally renowned Boston, Massachussetts, stained glass design company, Wilbur H. Burnham Studios, measure 35.2 linear feet and date from circa 1904-1991. The majority of the collection consists of project files for the studio's stained glass window contracts throughout the United States from the 1920s-1980s. In addition to project files, records include biographical material for the owners, correspondence relating to personal and studio business, general business and financial records, writings such as published articles by Wilbur H. Burnham, scrapbooks and other printed material documenting the history of the company, artwork including extensive watercolor design studies for stained glass, and photographic material.
Biographical material includes resume details and autobiographical notes for Burnham and Burnham, Jr., in addition to membership and fellow certificates.
Correspondence documents general studio business and includes correspondence with current and prospective clients, correspondence related to exhibitions, Burnham, Jr.'s activities on the Executive Committee of the America Arts Exposition, Inc., and the 1940 annual meeting of the Stained Glass Association of America and related business. Also found is some personal correpondence with friends and colleagues. Of note are 4 letters from stained glass artist Charles J. Connick giving his opinions on other stained glass artists, including Burnham, and a letter written by sculptor and designer, Joseph D. Portanova.
General business files include personnel records, records relating to a studio apprenticeship in stained glass design, a 1932 inventory of the studios, and leases and other legal documentation.
Writings include published articles by Burnham, in addition to draft typescripts for a book on stained glass which was never published, and research notes used as background material for stained glass studies. These notes include a number of pencil sketches.
19 diaries and journals consist of travel diaries and date books containing notes on daily appointments, financial notes, and addresses.
Project files form the bulk of the collection and document projects in circa 250 locations throughout the United States and Bellau, France, from the 1920s-1980s through correspondence with clients, architects and builders, contracts, purchase orders, building plans, sketches, scattered photographs and some printed material. Of particular note are extensive files on stained glass for New York's Cathedral of Saint John the Divine, Saint Mary's Cathedral in Peoria, Illinois, Saint Martin's Church in Providence, Rhode Island, and the National Cathedral in Washington D. C. The series also includes a group of contract files for the company Reynolds, Francis & Rohnstock (later Joseph G. Reynolds), a contemporary of Wilbur H. Burnham Studios.
Financial records include payment and receipt journals, expense reports, bills, account books and general ledgers which provide finanical documentation from the 1930s to the 1980s.
Printed material includes news clippings about Burnham studios and stained glass in general, in addition to source material used in subject research.
Additional newsclippings about Burnham Studios can be found in three scrapbooks which also house announcements and invitations, and scattered photographs. One scrapbook contains photographs of windows designed by the studios for the Church of Saint Vincent De Paul in Los Angeles, California.
Artwork and sketchbooks include some artwork by Burnham, Jr., such as pencil and ink sketches, life drawings, and some watercolors. The bulk of the series consists of watercolor design studies on board for many of the studio's projects documented in the project files. Also found are some stained glass design sketches and cartoons, primarily in pencil and charcoal with scattered watercolors, as well as seven folders of material used in creating stained glass patterns and templates.
Photographic material includes photos of Burnham and Burnham, Jr., and of studio work in progress, as well as photographs of artwork, primarily of stained glass created for a significant number of the studio's contracts.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 11 series:
Series 1: Biographical Materials, circa 1930s-circa 1970s (Boxes 1, 27; 4 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1920s-1991 (Box 1; 0.9 linear feet)
Series 3: General Business Files, 1930s-1970 (Box 2; 0.38 linear feet)
Series 4: Writings and Notes, 1920s-1950s (Box 2; 6 folders)
Series 5: Diaries and Journals, circa 1920s-circa 1960s (Box 2; 4 folders)
Series 6: Project Files, 1916-1980s (Boxes 2-12, 42; 10.6 linear feet)
Series 7: Financial Records, 1928-1982 (Boxes 13-14; 1.14 linear feet)
Series 8: Printed Material, circa 1920s-1980s (Boxes 14-15, 27-28; 1.89 linear feet)
Series 9: Scrapbooks, circa 1920s-circa 1970s (Boxes 15-16, 28, OVs 48-49, BV 84; 1.05 linear feet)
Series 10: Artwork and Sketchbooks, circa 1920s-circa 1980s (Boxes 16-23, 29-39, OVs 50-73, 85, RD 83; 13.15 linear feet)
Series 11: Photographic Materials, circa 1904-circa 1980s (Boxes 23-26, 29, 40-41, 43-47, OVs 74-82; 5.8 linear feet)
American Art Expositions (Firm); Burnham, Wilbur Herbert, 1887-1974; Burnham, Wilbur Herbert, Jr., 1913-1984; Connick, Charles J., 1875-1945; Joseph G. Reynolds Associates; Portanova, Joseph Domenico, 1909-1979; Reynolds, Francis, and Rohnstock; Reynolds, Joseph G., 1886-1972; Stained Glass Association of America; Church architecture--United States; Church decoration and ornament--United States; Decorative arts; Diaries; Glass painting and staining--United States; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks; Sketches; Stained glass artists-Massachusetts; Watercolors
- Biographical Materials, circa 1930s-circa 1970s; Series 1; 4 Folders Boxes 1, 27
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical materials include resume details for Burnham and Burnham, Jr., and autobiographical notes handwritten by Burnham. Also found are fellow and membership certificates for the Stained Glass Association of America, a fellow certificate for the Royal Society for the Encouragement of Arts, Manufacturers and Commerce, and a mounted blank check given as a Christmas gift to Burnham.
  - Awards and Certificates, circa 1950s-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    oversized material housed in Box 27
  - Biographical Material, circa 1930s-circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mounted Blank Check, Christmas Gift to Wilbur H. Burnham, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Awards and Certificates, circa 1950s-1972 (Box 27)
    oversized material from Box 1, F 1
- Correspondence, 1920s-1991; Series 2; 0.9 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence relates to general studio business and includes correspondence with current and prospective clients, general inquiries, financial material, plans for exhibitions. Also found are four letters from stained glass artist, Charles J. Connick, and one letter from sculptor and designer, Joseph D. Portanova.
  Personal correspondence concerns matters such as involvement with alumni and business associations, personal exchanges regarding stained glass art and techniques, correspondence with friends, arrangements for travel and events, and correspondence regarding Christmas greetings.
  Also found is material relating to the American Arts Exposition, Inc., a corporation formed to advise agencies and sponsoring groups in gathering together works of art representing American fine and related arts. Burnham, Jr., served on the Executive Committee of the organization and his files include correspondence, notes, lists of members and exhibition planning documentation.
  Correspondence relating to Stained Glass Association of America business, particularly the Association's 1940 annual meeting in New York City, can also be found here.
  Arrangement note
  Records are arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - American Arts Exposition, Inc., 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - American Arts Exposition, Inc., Secretary's Notes, circa 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, General, 1930s-1991 (Box 1, Folder 8-16)
  - Correspondence, Glass Companies, 1950s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence/Miscellaneous, 1930s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, Personal, 1920s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 23-25)
  - Correspondence, Personal Business, 1930s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
  - Letters from Connick, Charles J., 1930s (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Letter from Portanova, Joseph D., 1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Prospects, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
  - Society of Arts and Crafts, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Stained Glass Association of America (Box 1)
    - Annual Meetings, 1940; 1939 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Constitution and By-Laws, 1945; 1939; 1926 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence, 1929-1944 (Box 1, Folder 31-34)
    - Correspondence, Annual Meeting, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 35-37)
    - Correspondence, Sheldon Dinner Acceptance, 1930s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Correspondence, Sheldon Dinner Refusal, 1930s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Testimony Before Committee for Reciprocity Information re: Trade Agreements, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- General Business Files, 1930s-1970; Series 3; 0.38 Linear feet Box 2
  Files relate primarily to employees and include records of those selected for an apprenticeship in stained glass work that the company was approved to offer in 1945. Other employee records relate to pay and on the job injuries and include a set of index cards recording skills, experience, and dates of employment. Also found is a handwritten inventory of the contents of the studio in 1932, and legal material including records of the studio lease on Boylston Street, Boston.
  - Apprenticeship, 1940s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Copley Society of Boston, Lists of Members, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Employee Records, 1940s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Employee Records, Index Cards, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Forms and Letterhead, circa 1930s-circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Index Cards of Contacts, circa 1930s-circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Inventory of Studio, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Labels from Display, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Leases and Loan, 1940s-1972 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Legal Material, 1930s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Notebooks, circa 1967 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Records of Employee Time Spent on Jobs, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
- Writings and Notes, 1920s-1950s; Series 4; 6 Folders Box 2
  Writings include draft typescripts for a book on stained glass, and possibly other articles, by Burnham that were never completed and/or published. Copies of published articles by Burnham include: "Stained Glass Construction and Details," (1924), "The Clerestory Apse Windows" (of Riverside Church in New York City; 1929), a catalog for "An Exhibition of Stained Glass by American Art-Craftsmen" at Springfield Art Museum (1931), "The Spiritual Significance of a Stained Glass Window" (1945), and "the Art and Craft of Stained Glass" (1951). Also found is a typescript of Burnham, Jr.'s thesis, submitted at Yale University, "The Rebirth of Secular Stained Glass." Typescripts and notes appear to consist of research notes for stained glass studies, and include a group of typescripts on the history of Detroit, with pencil sketches.
  - Drafts for Book/Articles by Wilbur H. Burnham, Sr., circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Published Writings by Wilbur H. Burnham, Sr., 1920s-1950s (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Thesis by Wilbur H. Burnham, Jr., "The Rebirth of Secular Stained Glass,", 1939 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Typescripts and Notes, circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 19-21)
- Diaries and Journals, circa 1920s-circa 1960s; Series 5; 4 Folders Box 2
  Diaries and journals consist of 19 items that are a combination of journals with entries describing travel, including a trip to Europe in 1955, and date books containing daily appointments, financial notations, and addresses.
  Items are arranged in chronological order.
  - Diaries and Journals, circa 1920s-circa 1960s (Box 2, Folder 22-25)
- Project Files, 1916-1980s; Series 6; 10.6 Linear feet Boxes 2-12, 42
  Project, or "Job," files provide documentation of contracts for approximately 250 locations held by Burnham Studios throughout the United States and in Bellau, France, from the 1920s-1980s. Files typically include correspondence with clients, architects and builders, contracts, purchase orders, building plans, sketches, scattered photographs and some printed material. Found at the beginning of the series are some files relating to projects in general, including correspondence and job orders with metal window specialists, Chas. Haas Company; 2 sets of index cards listing project numbers and materials used; records of repair contracts; and a set of completed contracts for the firm Reynolds, Francis & Rohnstock from 1920s-1960s.
  The series contains significant documentation for the following projects in particular: New York's Cathedral of Saint John the Divine, Saint Mary's Cathedral in Peoria, Illinois, Saint Martin's Church in Providence, Rhode Island, and the Washington National Cathedral in Washington D. C.
  See below for Appendix: List of Numbered Contracts
  Arrangement of this series reflects the studio's main system for organizing project files alphabetically by name of the town in which the job site was located. It can be assumed that all folder titles containing references to letters elsewhere in the collection (e.g. "Repairs, A-C, E,") also follow that system of arrangement. Beginning in the 1920s Burnham Studios began assigning numbers to contracts and several copies of a list of contracts by number were found in the collection. That list is provided below and allows for cross-referencing (albeit incomplete) of the projects arranged by location in this series with the design studies found in Series 10: Artwork and Sketchbooks. The list was transcribed from hand-written records which were incomplete and sometimes illegible.
  Appendix: List of Numbered Contracts
  1. Pitsburgh, E. Liberty Presbyterian Church, 3 figure windows
  2. Pittsburgh, E. Liberty Presbyterian Church
  3. Sample, Liturgical Arts Exhibition
  4. New York, Cath. St. John Divine, Missionary sample
  5. Chevy Chase, Shrine Most Blessed Sacrament
  6. Boston, Old South, repair corridor windows
  7. Boston, Old South, 30 clerestory windows
  8. Sample, duplicate Liturgial Arts #3
  9. Boston, Old South rose
  10. Worcester, All Saints Church, chancel
  11. Boston, N. E. Mutual
  12. Fall River, St. Mark's Church
  14. Albany, St. Andrew's
  15. Worcester, All Saints Church (Thompson) duplicate (restored after fire)
  16. Buffalo, Westminster Presbyterian
  17. Transparencies, Dusky Dancer
  18. Quincy, Mausoleum, Long & Saunders
  19. Worcester, All Saints Church, aisle, St. Martin of Tours
  20. Greenwood, Union Church
  21. Illegible
  22. New York, Cath. St. John Divine, Lawyers
  23. Worcester, All Saints Church, Sample Mr. Robb
  24. Waban, Union Church
  25. New York, Cath. St. John Divine, Ecclesiastical
  26. Worcester, All Saints Church aisle, St. Elizabeth of Hungary
  27. New York, Cath. St. John Divine, clerestory (Lawyers Bay-St. Paul; Ecclesiastical Bay-Moses)
  28. New York, Cath. St. John Divine, clerestory (St. Augustine, St. Aidan)
  29. New York, St. Thomas Chapel
  30. Transparency, Erica
  31. Transparency, Dickey, Coats of Arms
  32. Boston, Tremont Temple, Erica
  33. Northeast Harbor, St. Mary's by the Sea
  34. Albany, Westminster Presbyterian, Herrick Mem'l aisle, Faith
  35. Detroit, Backus, design
  36. New York, Cath. St. John Divine, aisle sample #25
  37. New York, Cath. St. John Divine, clerestory sample #28
  38. Cambridge, St. Peter's
  39. Detroit, Backus
  40. Worcester, All Saints-Thompson
  41. Needham, Legion
  42. Christ circle
  43. Sunapee, N. H. Private Chapel, Crowther
  44. Durham, N. C. (see also #19 old groups of numbers)
  45. Needham, Congregational, Long Church
  46. Sample, Madonna and Child
  47. Salisbury, MD, St. Peter's
  48. Mechanicville, NY, Frye
  49. Transparency, Portia and the Prince, King Lear Spring
  50. Resnick-Roslindale-Church Saviour
  51. Melrose, Trinity Church
  52. Dobbs Ferry, N. Y., Ferncliff Chapel
  53. Peoria, IL, St. Mary's Cath.
  54. Clinton, St. John's Choir windows
  55. Beverly, Appleton, circle
  56. Repair, National Casket Co.
  57. Au Sable Forks
  58. Cincinnati, Calvary Church
  59. Norwich, CO, repair
  60. Lanesboro, St. Luke's Church
  61. Repair, Lantern, Mrs. George Hall
  62. Beverly, St. Peter's Gove
  63. Belfast, ME, Matthews Brothers
  64. Los Angeles, Dohney Mausoleum
  65. Barharbor, Lingee Memorial
  66. Peoria, IL, Lady Chapel
  67. Tozzer House, Fry, Cambridge
  68. Detroit, Central M. E. Church
  69. Bishop O'Leary's House
  70. Concord, St. Paul's School, fifteen medallions
  71. Repair, Melrose, Trinity Church
  72. Winter Park, Rollins College
  73. Repair, lampshade, Smith
  74. Swampscott, Ch. Holy Name
  75. Marblehead, Unitarian Church
  76. Grand Rapids, Klise Chapel chancel window
  77. Hadley, South, Mount Holyoke Chapel
  78. Peoria, Illinois, roses
  79. Clinton, St. John's, 3 sanctuary, 2 chapel, 2 front
  80. Concord, N. H. - Adams
  81. St. Augustine, FL
  82. Salt Lake City-Fry
  83. Winter Park, Rollins College-Erasmus, John, Eliz. of Hungary
  84. Cincinnati, Trailer cathedral-Bishop Hobson
  85. Mechanicville-Fry (2 aisles)
  86. Sample, Eve from Peoria Lady Chapel
  87. Transparencies, Erica 2 coat of arms and 2 trans.
  88. Northampton-Prof. Putnam
  89. Albany, N.Y., St. Andrew's
  90. Allentown, PA, St John's Ev. Luth. Church
  91. Hampton, NH, Congregational Church
  92. Northampton, Smith College, Library Chapel, Irving & Casson
  93. Repair, Brookline, St. Paul's
  94. San Francisco, St. Ives' Law Club, St. Ignatius
  95. Brookline, Mr. Page, 80 Seaver St.
  96. Brookline, Leyden Congregational Church, West transept
  97. Sample, Duplicate #46
  98. Peoria, IL, St. Thomas More Chapel
  99. Brocton, Bart Bonner
  100. Sample, Gowns
  101. Sample, duplicate of #52
  102. Processes for exhibition-how window is made
  103. Repair-Long & Saunders
  104. Repair
  105. Brookline, Harvard Church
  106. Coat of Arms, Bishop Schlarman
  107. Peoria, St. Mary's Cath. 12 nave windows
  108. Medway
  109. Cleveland, Ohio, Trinity Cathedral, aisle windows
  110. Elyria, St. Andrew's Episcopal Church
  111. Braintree, Emmanuel Church
  112. West Roxbury, Church Holy Name
  114. Montpelier, St. Augustine's Ch.
  115. Winchester, Ch. Epiphany
  116. Exeter, NH, repair
  117. Bradford, VT-Congregational Church
  118. Transparency, colored pieces
  119. Repair, Chestnut Hill, Ch. Redeemer
  120. Pittsburgh, PA, Hunt Residence
  121. Wellesley, College
  122. Repair, Collens
  123. Melrose, Repair
  124. Newport, RI, St. George's School
  125. Brookline, St. Paul's, repair
  126. Wrentham, Trinity Episcopal, repair
  127. Repair, Leominster, Pilgrim Congregational
  128. Christ Chapel, Brookline-Sears 1st repairs
  129. Sample, Dagit, Philadelphia
  130. Harrisburg, Pine Street Church
  131. Repair, Stafford Springs, Molitoris
  132. Repair, Holy Name, W. Roxbury, basement
  133. Repair, Chestnut Hill, Ch. Redeemer
  134. Repair, Leominster, Methodist
  135. Repair, Medfield, Congregational
  136. Repair, New Badford, Weber
  137. Church Hill, Md., St. Luke's
  138. Mt. Vernon, O., Mercy Hospital
  139. Cincinnati, Calvary Ch. transept
  140. Transparency, St. Francis of Assisi (WHB)
  141. Jamaica Plain, Unitarian Cong. Ch. repair
  142. Transparency, Fry
  143. Transparency, WHB Owl
  144. Concord, St. Paul's School Shields
  145. New Haven, CO, St. Thomas Ch.
  146. Greensbury, 1st Pres. Ch.
  147. Albany, St. Andrews, aisle
  148. Sample, Jr. auto panel
  149. Repair, Ch. New Jerusalem
  150. Milford, Trinity Ch. design
  151. Greensburgh (Taylor)
  152. Transparency, Sea Horse
  153. Repair, Cambridge
  154. Lynn, Ch. Incarnation
  155. Miss Frye., Mechanicsville, NY
  156. Webster, Church of Reconciliation, Col. Wilson
  157. Sample, Tricker Gallery, Exhibition, Kotzian Cruifixion
  158. Montpelier-St. Augustine's-Crosby
  159. Springfield, Hillcrest Mausoleum, Heydt
  160. Brookline, Christ Church (Sears)
  161. Transparency, St. Francis two ovals
  162. Brookline, Christ Chapel (Sears) reglazing rose
  163. Newport, St. George's Chapel
  164. Webster, Church of Reconcilliation, Chancel, 2 grisaille windows
  165. Maynard, Heffernan, circular and 2 quarries
  166. Transparency ship no paint
  167. Washington Cathedral, Choir clerestory-Peter Paul, Annunciation
  168. Transparency, Owl
  169. Swampscott, St. John's Convent repair
  170. New Bedford, St. Joseph's Ch., Maginnis & Walsh
  171. Transparency, St. Francis, Gothic
  172. Sample, auto panel Jr., framing & boxing
  173. Transparency, Jr. Mexican dancer
  174. Transparency, Chocolate soldiers
  175. Transparency, Knave of Spades-Erica
  176. Transparency, Queen of Hearts-Erica
  177. Maynard, 10 aisle windows
  178. Peoria, St. Mary's Cathedral, St. Thomas More Chapel, murals
  179. Roxbury, Jewish Synagogue (now 209)
  180. Worcester Tech, 29 medallions
  181. Repair, Charleston, SC
  182. New Bedford, Holy Name Parish
  183. Finkelstein, 2 cabinet doors, king and queen